ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
Let's see… Long-range magic
这个嘛…长距离魔法呢
is made by combining three factors that are required of all mages.
是所有魔法使必备的三要素组合技
One is your supply of mana, another is the power to shoot it,
一是你的魔力来源 其次是发射的力道
and then the power to control it.
再来是操控魔力的力量
You know this much, right?
这些你都知道吧？
Yes.
是
Earlier, your magic dispersed midway.
刚刚你的魔力半路就散了
That indicates that you don't have enough mana and shooting power.
那就表示你的魔力跟发射的力道不够
That isn't something you can resolve overnight.
这不是你一时半会就能办到的事情
Regardless of your talent, you have to work on it over several years.
尽管你有天赋 还是得花上几年的时间磨练才行
But it seems you have a strong ability to control your mana.
不过你操控魔力的能力看起来很强
People usually have a hard time with it,
一般人要操控魔力都不容易
but I don't think you have to worry about that.
不过我认为这一点你不用担心
Just take your time.
慢慢来就好
Okay.
好的
How is Fern's training going?
菲伦的修行顺利吗？
In four years, she reached a level that would normally take ten years.
才四年她就完成 常人十年才能达到的门坎
She's too engrossed in it. It's not a very good thing.
这孩子太过沉迷了 这可不是好事
Nowadays, she's cooped up in the forest the whole time.
最近她一直窝在森林里呢
She must love magic for sure.
她一定是很喜欢魔法
But she's still not even close to becoming a full-fledged mage.
不过她要成为 独当一面的魔法使还差的远呢
I'll finish deciphering this grimoire before that.
在那之前我就会解读完这本书了
Is that so…?
这样啊…
Hey, Heiter…
海塔 话说…
This grimoire probably--
这本魔导书应该…
Heiter?
海塔？
Don't look like that.
不要露出那种表情
It was a miracle that I was even able to move normally up until now.
我到现在还能正常行动已经是奇迹了
I'll hurry up and decipher the grimoire.
我会尽快解读完魔导书的
Thank you.
麻烦你了
Fern, put a pause on training.
菲伦 修行暂停一下
Heiter collapsed. Go and stay by his side.
海塔倒下了 去他身旁陪他吧
I still haven't pierced through the rock.
我还没打穿那颗岩石
That's something you'll be able to do one day for sure. Right now--
那件事你迟早有一天会做到 现在…
It can't be "one day"!
不能是“迟早有一天”！
If I wait until that day,
等到那天到来
Master Heiter will die.
海塔大人就不在了
He saved my life.
他救了我的命
It would be a waste for you to die now.
现在死了就太可惜了
A waste?
可惜？
It's been quite a while now,
已经是很久以前的事了
but I lost an old friend.
我的一位老朋友去世了
Unlike me, he was always so upstanding.
他不像我 他为人总是很正直
He was the kind of person who could never ignore someone in need.
他是那种看到别人有难 就无法置之不理的人
If he was still alive, instead of me,
如果活着的人是他而不是我
he could've saved many people.
他一定会拯救很多人
I am not like him,
我跟他不一样
so I planned to live the rest of my life in peace.
我打算安稳平静地度过余生
But one day, I realized something.
但有一天 我明白了一件事
If I die like this,
如果我就这样死去
everything he taught me about courage, determination, and friendship,
他教会我的勇气、意志跟友谊
and even our precious memories
还有我们珍贵的回忆
might disappear from this world as well.
也会从这个世上消失
If you also have
如果你也拥有
precious memories,
珍贵的回忆
I believe it'd be a waste for you to die.
我觉得就这么死掉太可惜了
Master Heiter was always worried
海塔大人总是很担心
about dying and leaving me behind.
死后会留下我独自一人
He did what was right.
那位大人做了正确的事
I don't want him to regret saving me.
我不想让他后悔救了我
Whether I become a mage or not doesn't matter.
当不当魔法使其实无所谓
Finding a way to survive on my own
找到自己一个人也能生存的办法
is my way of repaying him.
就是我报答他的方式
I want him to be glad that he saved me
我希望他会庆幸自己当初救下了我
and know that I'll be fine.
并且对我能够放心
You remember everything I taught you, right?
你记得我教过的一切吧？
Yes.
是的
Then do as you please.
那你想怎么做就怎么做吧
There was nothing about spells for resurrecting the dead or immortality.
里面没有任何复活魔法 或是永生不死的魔法
Is that right?
这样啊
You knew?
你早就知道了？
The fear of death is unfathomable.
对死亡的恐惧是难以估量的
If such a thing existed, Ewig would've used it on himself.
真有那种东西的话 埃维希就会用在自己身上了吧
Then why…?
那为什么…
How is Fern?
菲伦怎么样了？
She's still rough around the edges,
虽然还稍嫌不足
but you can call her a fully-fledged mage.
不过已经可以算是 独当一面的魔法使了
Is that right. So I made it in time.
这样吗？不枉我撑到现在
She is no longer a burden is she, Frieren?
她已经不再是累赘了吧 芙莉莲？
Will you take her along with you on your travels?
你能带她跟你一起去旅行吗？
Sorry, Heiter. I can't do that.
对不起 海塔 这个我办不到
She'll just be a burden.
她只会是累赘而已
You tricked me, Heiter?
你算计我 海塔？
The fee for deciphering it is in the desk drawer.
解读的报酬放在桌子的抽屉里
Please leave by tonight.
你们今晚就离开吧
What do you mean?
什么意思？
As you can see, I don't have much time left.
如你所见 我已经时日不多了
I don't want her to go through the experience of losing someone again.
我不想让她再次经历失去他人的痛苦
Frieren, I leave Fern in your care.
芙莉莲 菲伦就交给你照顾了
Trying to act cool again, Heiter?
海塔 你又想装潇洒了？
Fern has already been prepared to say goodbye for a while now.
菲伦早就做好跟你告别的准备了
What you need to do before you die,
你死前应该做的
is give her a proper farewell
是好好跟那个孩子告别
and make as many memories with her as you can.
然后尽可能跟她多制造一点回忆
Frieren…
芙莉莲…
you really are such a kind girl.
你果然是温柔的孩子
Hey, why did you save Fern?
是说 你为什么要救菲伦？
Himmel the Hero would have done so.
是勇者辛美尔的话就会这么做
That's true.
说得没错
Well then,
那么我…
I guess I'll do the same.
也会这么做的
Thank you very much.
真的非常谢谢您
Because of you,
多亏有您
I was able to repay Master Heiter.
我才能够回报海塔大人的恩情
I was just tricked into it.
我纯粹是
By this corrupt priest.
被这个酒肉僧侣算计了
Okay, let's go.
好 出发吧
26 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者辛美尔逝世的26年后）
THE TURK REGION IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央诸国塔库地区）
That's enough, Fern.
可以了 菲伦
We're done.
结束了
What a lifesaver.
真是帮了大忙
This is the reward I promised.
这是说好的报酬
They're all very unassuming tasks…
都是些简单的工作呢…
This is what being an adventurer is like.
冒险家就是这样啊
What was the reward?
报酬是什么？
A folk spell.
民间魔法
It's a spell that produces hot tea.
是能变出热茶的魔法
Let's test it out later.
待会来试试看吧
Last time was a spell that removes rust from bronze statues.
上次是能 把铜像上的锈清理干净的魔法
Before that it was another spell.
在之前是把甜的葡萄
-For turning sweet grapes sour. -It's sour.
-变酸的魔法 -好酸
You keep collecting such strange spells.
您总是收集奇怪的魔法呢
It's my hobby.
因为是我的嗜好啊
Mistress Frieren, you must really love magic.
芙莉莲大人真的很喜欢魔法呢
To a moderate degree, just like you.
普普通通啦 就跟你一样
I think we're a little different.
我觉得我们有点不一样
We're the same.
是一样的
Are you sure you want to accept my offer?
你们真的愿意接受我的请求吗？
I'm just an herbalist,
我只是个药草学家
so I don't think I can teach you any new magic.
没有什么新魔法可以交给你们
That's fine.
没关系
I'd be happy if you'd just tell me about the vegetation of this region.
只要能告诉我这一带的植被分布就好
Here it is.
就是这里
It's a statue of Himmel the Hero.
是勇者辛美尔的铜像
It's in terrible shape, isn't it?
状况很糟 对吧？
There's only so much an old lady like me can do on my own.
我一个老太太也无法做什么
The people of the village don't care anymore.
村里的人也不关心这里了
-Mom! -Run!
-妈妈！ -快逃！
When our village was attacked by monsters,
村里被魔物袭击的时候
Master Himmel fought for us with all his might.
辛美尔大人为了我们拼上性命战斗
Treating him like this is just too cruel.
受到这种对待也太可怜了
No.
不会
He's getting what he deserves.
这是他自作自受
It's Himmel's fault for wanting fame.
是辛美尔自己想要出名的错
He should've said no when the villagers said they'd erect a statue.
村民说要为他立雕像时 明明可以拒绝的
Are you sure?
确定吗？
-Isn't this pose too handsome? -Who cares…
-这个姿势会不会太帅了？ -谁在乎啊…
He spent 18 hours picking a pose.
他花了十八个小时选姿势
-And he pissed off the artist. -I'm hungry!
-最后惹毛了工匠大叔 -肚子好饿！
In the end, he settled with a ridiculously standard pose.
结果最后决定用 这个笨蛋一样的普通姿势
What a strange story.
真是不可思议的故事
Now that I think about it, there was an elf mage in the party of heroes.
我现在才想起来 勇者一行中也有一名精灵魔法使
Well then, let's clean it up.
那么来清理一下吧
What a lifesaver.
真是帮了大忙
Magic is so amazing, isn't it?
魔法真的好厉害
There's not a speck of rust on the statue!
铜像上一点锈痕都没有了！
It needs a bit of color.
这里还少了点颜色点缀
Maybe I'll plant some flowers later.
以后来种点花好了
Mistress Frieren, you know the spell to create a field of flowers, right?
芙莉莲大人 我记得 您知道变出花田的魔法吧？
Yeah, maybe I'll plant some random flowers…
是啊 随便种点什么好了…
No, it should be Blue Moon Weeds.
不对 还是种苍月草的花好
What kind of flower is that?
那是什么样的花？
I don't know. I've never seen it before.
我不知道 我从来没见过
Then why…
那为什么…
It grows in Himmel's hometown.
那是辛美尔故乡的花
But you can't recreate flowers you've never seen.
可是您无法用魔法创造出没见过的花
Blue Moon Weed…
苍月草…
That name brings back memories.
真是令人怀念的名字
A long time ago,
很久以前
there used to be a colony of them deep in that forest.
那片森林深处有一处长满这种花
They don't grow around here anymore?
这一带已经没有了吗？
They've gone extinct.
已经灭绝了
I haven't heard of anyone spotting them on this continent for decades.
几十年来在这片大陆上 我都没听过还有谁看过那种花
I see.
原来如此
Fern, let's go.
菲伦 走吧
Okay.
好
You hid something.
你藏了什么东西？
I won't get mad, so show me.
我不会生气的 给我看看
Seed rats?
籽种鼠？
They're pests that eat seeds.
是以种子为食的害兽
I'll return them to the forest.
我会把它们带回森林里的
Okay, Fern, let's go search for Blue Moon Weeds.
好 菲伦 我们去找苍月草吧
Are you serious?
您是认真的？
Until just recently, there was a colony of them--
不久前还生长在这片森林深处…
That was decades ago.
是几十年前
It's still worth looking for.
但依旧值得去找找看
If we find the real one and analyze it,
如果能找到实物并加以分析
we'll acquire a spell that grows Blue Moon Weeds.
就可以得到让苍月草绽放的魔法了
Is it for Master Himmel?
是为了辛美尔大人才这么做的吗？
No.
不是
It's probably for myself.
肯定是为了我自己才做的
BLUE MOON WEED
（苍月草）
Mistress Frieren, it has been half a year since we began
芙莉莲大人 自从开始找苍月草之后
searching for the Blue Moon Weed.
已经过了半年的时间了
Yes, it has.
是啊
It's about time we widened our search.
差不多该开始扩大搜寻范围了
Oh,
噢
it's rare to see you by yourself.
很少见你一个人过来呢
It's been quite a while since you two came to this village.
你们来到村里也有好一段时间了
Did you find the Blue Moon Weed?
找到苍月草了吗？
Do you think we will find it?
你觉得我们能找到吗？
Mistress Frieren has an abnormal obsession toward magic.
芙莉莲大人对魔法 有种异于常人的执着
At this rate, she will keep searching for years, maybe decades.
照这样下去 不管是几年 或几十年她都会继续找下去
Mistress Frieren is a mage with the power to help many people.
芙莉莲大人是魔法使 拥有足以拯救很多人的力量
Spending time searching for something that doesn't exist
实在不应该花时间
is just unacceptable.
寻找不存在的东西
You're so young.
你还很年轻
Is my way of thinking wrong?
我这么想是错的吗？
I don't think so.
我并不这么认为
But Ms. Frieren must think differently.
可是芙莉莲小姐的想法可能不一样
However,
不过
she is much older than both of us,
她比我们都要年长的多
so if you tell her your honest feelings,
如果你诚实告诉她你的感受
I'm sure she'll understand.
我相信她会理解的
These seeds are of a related species that were
这是苍月草近缘种的种子
stored for medicinal use.
因为有医疗效果而被保存下来了
How about we plant these around Master Himmel's statue instead?
要不要在辛美尔大人 铜像附近改种这种花呢？
I understand, Fern.
我明白了 菲伦
Sorry to make you worry.
抱歉让你担心了
I'm not on my own anymore.
我再也不是自己一个人了
It's about time to stop.
是时候该收手了
I'll wrap things up in a little bit.
再找一阵子就结束吧
When you say "a little" how many years is that?
“一阵子”是指多少年呢？
Just a little.
就是一阵子而已
You really can't give up can you--
您真的不能放弃…
Let's follow it.
跟上去看看吧
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉莲大人
why do you collect spells?
您为什么要收集魔法呢？
-It's just a hobby. -It doesn't seem that way.
-纯粹兴趣罢了 -看起来不像啊
It's really just a hobby.
真的纯粹只是兴趣使然
Before, I used to be apathetic and lived without purpose.
只是以前我活得更懒散 生活也没有目标
Gross…
真恶心…
There was an idiot who praised me for the spells I collected.
曾经有个笨蛋 因为我收集的魔法而夸奖我
That's all.
仅此而已
That is a silly reason.
真是无聊的理由
It is.
没错
That's…
那是…
It's a petal.
是花瓣
Apparently, seed rats hide their food
据说籽种鼠会把食物藏在
in a safe place, away from their enemies.
远离敌人的安全地点
They're smart animals.
真是聪明的小动物
Not really.
也不见得呢
They hide them in so many places,
它们把食物藏在很多地方
so they forget where they hid them.
所以有时连自己都忘了藏在哪里
Blue Moon Weeds?
苍月草？
It's a flower from my hometown.
那是我故乡的花
It's really beautiful.
真的非常好看
Well, not as beautiful as me, though.
不过当然没有我这么好看了
We should get going.
差不多该走了
Frieren…
芙莉莲…
One day, I want to show you.
真希望有一天能让你看看
Yeah? Maybe someday.
是吗？有机会的话
I knew I'd find it, but I didn't expect so many.
我知道一定会找到 不过没料到有这么多就是了
Sorry it took so long, Himmel.
终于看到了 辛美尔
Who knew you would actually find them?
竟然真的找到了
Now I can make a spell for Blue Moon Weeds.
现在可以制作苍月草的魔法了
Why are you so committed to magic?
为什么您这么热衷于魔法呢？
I don't understand.
我真是不明白
You should know.
你应该也能懂的
You didn't give up on becoming a mage yourself.
毕竟你自己也没有放弃当魔法使
That's not true.
不是这样的
As long as I could acquire the strength to live on my own,
我只要能得到独立生存的力量
it could've been anything.
什么都可以
It didn't have to be magic.
也不一定要是魔法…
But you chose magic.
但你选了魔法啊
That's true.
这倒是
Who would have thought
真没想到
that I could see Blue Moon Weeds again?
我竟然可以再次看到苍月草
They're so beautiful.
真的好美啊
Thank you, Ms. Frieren.
谢谢你 芙莉莲小姐
I'm sure this statue will not be forgotten anymore.
我相信再也没有人会忘记这尊雕像了
I almost forgot…
差点忘了…
There.
好了
Oh my, how cute.
天啊 好可爱
All right, let's go now.
好 现在出发吧
That's too powerful.
那简直是强大过头了
Qual, the Elder Sage of Corruption.
腐败贤者古瓦尔
Okay, let's practice it.
好 那就来应用看看
Does this journey have a purpose?
这趟旅途有什么目标吗？
"Killing magic."
杀人魔法
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵